<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Metaviz Tutorials on Epiviz</title>
    <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Metaviz Tutorials on Epiviz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 14:12:05 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Metaviz Quick Overview</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 14:08:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/overview/</guid>
      <description>Metaviz is a tool for interactive visualization and exploration of metagenomic sequencing data. It provides a novel navigation tool for exploring hierarchical feature data that is coupled with multiple data visualizations including heatmaps, stacked bar charts, and scatter plots. Metaviz supports a flexible plugin framework so users can add new d3 visualizations. This post introduces the most compelling user interface features of Metaviz. An in-depth visual analysis using Metaviz can be found here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Differential Analysis with MetagenomeSeq and Metaviz</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/metagenomeseq/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 14:08:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/metagenomeseq/</guid>
      <description>Metaviz is a tool for interactive visualization and exploration of metagenomic sequencing data. It provides a novel navigation tool for exploring hierarchical feature data that is coupled with multiple data visualizations including heatmaps, stacked bar charts, and scatter plots. The metavizr package implements two-way communication between the R/Bioconductor computational genomics environment and Metaviz. Objects in an R/Bioconductor session can be visualized and explored using the Metaviz navigation tool and plots. In this post we show how to use metavizr and the metagenomeSeq Bioconductor package to perform a statistical and visual analysis of differential abundance of metagenomic data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visual Analysis of MSD16S Dataset</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/video_tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 14:08:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/video_tutorials/</guid>
      <description>Metaviz is a tool for interactive visualization and exploration of metagenomic sequencing data. It provides a novel navigation tool for exploring hierarchical feature data that is coupled with multiple data visualizations including heatmaps, stacked bar charts, and scatter plots. Metaviz supports a flexible plugin framework so users can add new d3 visualizations. This post shows how to use all the UI features of Metaviz to examine the Moderate to Severe childhood diaherrial disease (msd16s) dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Longitudinal Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/spline/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 14:08:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/spline/</guid>
      <description>Metaviz is a tool for interactive visualization and exploration of metagenomic sequencing data. It provides a novel navigation tool for exploring hierarchical feature data that is coupled with multiple data visualizations including heatmaps, stacked bar charts, and scatter plots. The metavizr package implements two-way communication between the R/Bioconductor computational genomics environment and Metaviz. Objects in an R/Bioconductor session can be visualized and explored using the Metaviz navigation tool and plots. In this post we show how to use metavizr and the metagenomeSeq Bioconductor package to analyze data from a longitudinal study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metaviz Docker Containers</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/usingdocker/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 14:08:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/usingdocker/</guid>
      <description>Setup and Installation Metaviz UI along with the webservices and the graph database are available as docker containers for self-hosting the application. We use docker-compose to manage these containers and the code is available at Metaviz Docker. The following provides the list of containers we use and the url to access them
   App Docker Container Name Port URL to access     Graph Database db 7474 http://localhost:7474   Web Services services 5000 http://localhost:5000   Metaviz UI ui 5500 http://localhost:5500   BioConductor bioc - -    For installing docker and docker-compose, Please follow the instructions at</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosting Data in Metaviz</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/hostingdata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 14:08:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/hostingdata/</guid>
      <description>Metaviz is a tool for interactive visualization and exploration of metagenomic sequencing data. It provides a novel navigation tool for exploring hierarchical feature data that is coupled with multiple data visualizations including heatmaps, stacked bar charts, and scatter plots. In this post we show how to load into a Metaviz backend database. We also talk about our plans to host a metagenomics data repository accessible at metaviz.cbcb.umd.edu.
Loading data using metavizR metavizr is an R-package that can serve data from an R session to a Metaviz browser instance and load data into a persistent graph database.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create a Diversity Plot with HMP2Data IBD Biopsy</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/diveristy_plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 14:08:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/diveristy_plot/</guid>
      <description>First on the Metaviz landing page click &amp;ldquo;Start App&amp;rdquo;
Next scroll to the bottom and select &amp;ldquo;ibd_biopsy_hmp2data&amp;rdquo; Choose &amp;ldquo;Add Visualization&amp;rdquo; and click &amp;ldquo;Heatmap&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot;
On the Heatmap click the Settings icon (middle) and in the Settings menu change &amp;ldquo;Plot Label&amp;rdquo; dropdown menu from &amp;ldquo;name&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; and toggle the button for &amp;ldquo;Row labels as color&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;On&amp;rdquo;
Select samples to visualize and click &amp;ldquo;Ok&amp;rdquo;
Choose &amp;ldquo;Add visualization&amp;rdquo; click &amp;ldquo;Diversity Box Plot&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Save plots on Metaviz</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/save_plots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 14:08:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/tutorials/metaviz/save_plots/</guid>
      <description>Each visualization on Metaviz has an option available to save and export it as png or svg. Choose the save option when you hover over a visualization in the top right corner.
Now choose a format to save the visualization. We recomment using png or svg as the export format.
finally, this downloads the visualization in the choosen format. For example the diversity box plot would generate a file below -</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
