<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Epiviz</title>
    <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Epiviz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 12:52:12 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://epiviz.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Epiviz Updates for Bioconductor 3.5 Release</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2017-05-01-epiviz-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 12:52:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2017-05-01-epiviz-update/</guid>
      <description>Bioconductor version 3.5 was released last month: http://bioconductor.org/news/bioc_3_5_release/. This Bioconductor version includes updates to epivizr and a new package, metavizr, for interactive visualization of metagenomic data. In this post we describe these, and take the opportunity to update on other developments in the Epiviz project.
What&amp;rsquo;s new!  epivizr updates Introducing Epiviz desktop application Metavizr now on R/Bioconductor Introducing epiviz webcomponents    Save and Restart an epivizr session</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISO: Data Scientist/Programmer</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2015-09-15-hiring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 10:52:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2015-09-15-hiring/</guid>
      <description>UPDATED: This position is now filled
We&amp;rsquo;re looking for a Data Scientist to make Epiviz better, stronger and faster! This is a full-time position (officially Faculty Research Assistant) within the Center for Bioinformatics and Computational Biology (CBCB) at the University of Maryland in College Park. You will work along faculty in CBCB and the Human-Computer Interaction Lab in developing state-of-the-art genomic data visual analytics software tools.
##What you will do:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Architecture and design paper in Biovis &#39;15</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2015-08-17-biovis15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 10:52:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2015-08-17-biovis15/</guid>
      <description>Our paper detailing the architecture and design of Epiviz is now available on the BMC Bioinformatics site. It is published in a supplement containing a good number of interesting papers from the Biovis &amp;lsquo;15 conference held as a satellite meeting of the ISMB 2015 conference. We also presented our Nature Methods paper on Epiviz in the highlights track at ISMB. Slides for that talk are available on github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenomic visualization in Nature Methods News and Comment</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2015-08-17-natmethods_news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 10:52:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2015-08-17-natmethods_news/</guid>
      <description>Epiviz was highlighted in a recent Nature Methods News and Comment piece on visualization of epigenomic data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using BED files with epiviz</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-12-18-bedtools/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 10:52:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-12-18-bedtools/</guid>
      <description>On a twitter exchange I showed A. Quinlan how to use epivizr to load data from a custom bed file. Here is the code I gave him:
library(epivizr) library(rtracklayer) # download example bed file download.file(&amp;#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/arq5x/bedtools/master/data/aluY.hg19.bed.gz&amp;#34;, destfile=&amp;#34;test.bed.gz&amp;#34;, method=&amp;#34;curl&amp;#34;) # start UI mgr &amp;lt;- startEpiviz(workspace=&amp;#34;mi9NojjqT1l&amp;#34;) # import bed file gr &amp;lt;- import(BEDFile(&amp;#34;test.bed.gz&amp;#34;)) # drop data from unplaced contigs gr &amp;lt;- keepSeqlevels(gr, paste0(&amp;#34;chr&amp;#34;,c(1:22,&amp;#34;X&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;Y&amp;#34;))) # add track with bed file data dev &amp;lt;- mgr$addDevice(gr, &amp;#34;example bed&amp;#34;) # finish up mgr$stopServer() Also at https://gist.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New epivizr release</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-10-31-new-epivizr-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 10:52:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-10-31-new-epivizr-release/</guid>
      <description>Version 1.4 of epivizr was released as part of the new Bioconductor 3.0 release. There are a good number of new features in epivizr in this release, including the ability of running the Epiviz UI within R, making R/Bioconductor capable of running it&amp;rsquo;s own genome browser!
Running epiviz as a standalone Previous versions of epivizr used the {{ site.epiviz }} web application hosted at the University of Maryland as the front-end for UI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Code Customization Feature for Visualizations</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-10-28-new-feature-code-edit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 13:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-10-28-new-feature-code-edit/</guid>
      <description>See it in Epiviz 4 See it in Epiviz 3 See it in Epiviz 2  Now visualizations&amp;rsquo; code can be customized in the UI, based on user needs!
To do it, simply click on the Edit code button on any of the available charts: Select the method(s) you want to edit. Only the methods corresponding to this particular instance of the chart will be modified. For example, in the MA Plot at http://epiviz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Clustering Feature for Heatmap Plots</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-10-28-new-feature-clustering/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-10-28-new-feature-clustering/</guid>
      <description>See it in Epiviz 4 See it in Epiviz 3 See it in Epiviz 2  We implemented a new Clustering feature in the Heatmap Plot! You can use it to group together measurements using the values in the selected region.
For example, we selected the following samples in the gene expression barcode: kidney normal and tumor, lung normal and tumor, esophagus normal and tumor, breast normal and tumor, stomach normal and tumor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epiviz published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-08-03-epiviz-paper-published/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 19:46:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://epiviz.github.io/post/2014-08-03-epiviz-paper-published/</guid>
      <description>Our first paper describing the {{ site.epiviz }} system was published today in Nature Methods. From the abstract:
 Visualization is an integral aspect of genomics data analysis. Algorithmic-statistical analysis and interactive visualization are most effective when used iteratively. Epiviz (http://epiviz.cbcb.umd.edu/), a web-based genome browser, and the Epivizr Bioconductor package allow interactive, extensible and reproducible visualization within a state-of-the-art data-analysis platform.
 And the editor&amp;rsquo;s blurb:
 Integration of genome visualization with Bioconductor-based analysis tools allows rapid and interactive analysis of genomes, transcriptomes and epigenomes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>